Just as there are different ways
of entering the hierarchical or region states,
there are also
different ways of exiting.
So we have to take
a look at that as well.
On the one hand there is,
let's take a hierarchical state first, and
later again
a region state.
In the hierarchical states there is
the exit from the composite state
as
a whole.
This is, so to speak, the
counterpart to the standard entry, where you
just approach the overall state from the
outside and don't somehow pick out something inside.
And in the same way here would be
the exit from the composite state as a whole.
Without further
somehow marking
from which sub-state one would
like to leave the overall state.
Then there is the possibility to
exit directly from a specific sub-state.
This corresponds or would be dual
to the explicit entry into a sub-state.
And then there were the two variants
shallow and deep history at the entry.
There is nothing corresponding
to them at the exit.
Yes, at the exit possibly something is
noted, in order to fall back at
the re-entry about history then on information, where
we have been last in this state altogether.
But with the
exit arrows themselves,
there are no additional variants for
history entry, history exit or so.
So there's just these two
options here at the hierarchical state.
And what do they
mean in each case?
So the exit from a
hierarchical state as a whole, simply
means as soon as the
trigger associated with the transition.
Yes, there could be
a trigger on each here.
And as soon as that takes
place, the overall state is simply exited.
No matter where one, in which concrete
sub-state one is here at the moment.
One simply leaves
the overall state.
What about when you
exit a specific sub-state?
Well then this transition, which probably
has a trigger on it, is
only taken/selected at all
if you are actually currently
in the specific sub-state you
are supposed to exit from.
So in our example diagram this would be
the state E, because this arrow goes from E.
I.e., we can, if there is
a trigger on here and the entry
is to select this arrow/transition only
if we are actually currently in E.
If we are currently in C or
D, then we cannot trigger this exit.
Besides that, yes,
there is another possibility.
An exit point as well as end states
or terminators over which we can also exit.
But these are
not treated here.
So we will only
need these two exit possibilities.
What this means concretely for
an example would be about this.
So, if we have here
such a state that is composed.
And we have one
exit from the overall state.
Then that actually corresponds
to three arrows in the
case, namely that we could have explicitly specifically
exited from B, from C, and from D.
These three exits from specific
sub-states are replaced by a
single exit from
the overall state.
Because then we don't have to say
where we are in the sub-state right now.
And this is exactly where we
save arrows in our overall/wristwatch example,
because there also have just such entries
and exits from or between overall states.
Instead of having arrows for
every combination of sub-state and sub-state.
That's exactly the goal of
this kind of entries and
exits, that we save
transitions in the representation.
And here, this very
example corresponds to that.
This would be when
we don't have regions.
Now we still have to
look at, what happens if
we have a region state
and we exit from that?
Then there is also the exit
from the composite state as a whole.
Then we would
just leave no
matter what sub-states we are
in right now in the regions.
There is the exit from
a sub-state, which is now
just located in one
of the possibly several regions.
And there is additionally
the exit over union,
essentially a counterpart to
the entrance over a fork.
Histories are here again not relevant
with the exit as somehow representation possibility.
What do now these exit
possibilities mean with region states?
Well, if we want to exit
again from the state as a
whole, then this
is simply always possible.
Then simply in each region
the sub-state present there is left.
So no matter in which sub-states
we are in the individual regions,
we can always choose
this exit from the whole.
What is specific about
exit from a sub-state?
Well, if we have something like this
situation, then we are only allowed to leave
the region state if we are actually
at the corresponding state in this region.
Yes so we would be allowed to leave the regions state
altogether if we are here in B and here in C.
Or if we are here
in B and here D.
But not if we are here in
A and here in C or D.
So the composite
state is left
only if one is
actually in the state/substate
left by this arrow
in the corresponding region.
In the regions parallel to it,
one can be in any state.
So in the concrete case it was
like this, we would only be able to
exit if we are actually
in B in the first region.
That would be this
case and this case.
And this case
now, it's explicitly stated
which sub-state we should
be in per region.
And then accordingly,
the rule is also.
We can leave the
composite state via the union
exactly when we are in the
appropriately labeled state in each region.
So in the example we could exit only
when we are actually in B and D.
Not if we are in
B and C or something.
If we are in B and C,
then we may exit over here, exit
over here, but
not over here.